<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-GB"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nime.org/nime/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://nime.org/nime/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-GB" /><updated>2024-01-12T03:10:32+00:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/feed.xml</id><title type="html">NIME</title><subtitle>The International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression gathers researchers and musicians from all over the world to share their knowledge and late-breaking work on new musical interface design.</subtitle><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><entry><title type="html">NIME2020 Royal Birmingham Conservatoire</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/announcement/conference/2019/07/08/NIME20announce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NIME2020 Royal Birmingham Conservatoire" /><published>2019-07-08T01:10:13+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-08T01:10:13+01:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/announcement/conference/2019/07/08/NIME20announce</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/announcement/conference/2019/07/08/NIME20announce/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://nime2020.bcu.ac.uk">Announcing <strong>NIME2020</strong></a>! July 21-25, Royal Birmingham Conservatoire, UK.</p>

<p><a href="http://nime2020.bcu.ac.uk"><img src="/nime/assets/logos/nime2020.png" alt="NIME2020 Logo" /></a></p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="announcement" /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing NIME2020! July 21-25, Royal Birmingham Conservatoire, UK.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NIME2019 Wrapup</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/wrapup/conference/2019/07/01/NIME19-wrapup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NIME2019 Wrapup" /><published>2019-07-01T01:10:13+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T01:10:13+01:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/wrapup/conference/2019/07/01/NIME19-wrapup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/wrapup/conference/2019/07/01/NIME19-wrapup/"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations and thanks to the team at UFRGS, Porto Alegre, for a wonderful NIME2019 and to everybody who gathered from around the world to present, perform, listen, and discuss!</p>

<p>We would like to make a special mention of the award winners from this year’s NIME:</p>

<p>And finally, we are very much looking forward to NIME 2020 in Birmingham next year!</p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="wrapup" /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Congratulations and thanks to the team at UFRGS, Porto Alegre, for a wonderful NIME2019 and to everybody who gathered from around the world to present, perform, listen, and discuss! We would like to make a special mention of the award winners from this year’s NIME: And finally, we are very much looking forward to NIME 2020 in Birmingham next year!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NIME 2019, Porto Alegre, Brazil</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/announcement/2017/12/01/NIME19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NIME 2019, Porto Alegre, Brazil" /><published>2017-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/announcement/2017/12/01/NIME19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/announcement/2017/12/01/NIME19/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to NIME 2019 in Porto Alegre, Brazil, 3-6 June 2019.</p>

<div class="video">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CMSripnGg9U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" title="Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>The International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression gathers researchers and musicians from all over the world to share their knowledge and late-breaking work on new musical interface design. The conference started out as a workshop at the <a href="https://www.acm.org/sigchi/">Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</a> (CHI) in 2001. Since then, an annual series of international conferences have been held around the world, hosted by research groups dedicated to interface design, human-computer interaction, and computer music.</p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="announcement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to NIME 2019 in Porto Alegre, Brazil, 3-6 June 2019. The International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression gathers researchers and musicians from all over the world to share their knowledge and late-breaking work on new musical interface design. The conference started out as a workshop at the Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) in 2001. Since then, an annual series of international conferences have been held around the world, hosted by research groups dedicated to interface design, human-computer interaction, and computer music.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NIME 2015 - Call for works</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2014/11/17/nime-2015-call-for-works/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NIME 2015 - Call for works" /><published>2014-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2014/11/17/nime-2015-call-for-works</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2014/11/17/nime-2015-call-for-works/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://nime2015.lsu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/2015nimelogo_transparent.png"><img src="https://nime2015.lsu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/2015nimelogo_transparent.png" alt="2015nimelogo_transparent" /></a></p>

<p>May 31 – June 3, 2015
Louisiana State University
Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA</p>

<p><a href="http://nime2015.lsu.edu">http://nime2015.lsu.edu</a></p>

<p>Download the Call for Works 
<a href="https://nime2015.lsu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/NIMECallForWorks2015.pdf">here</a>.
Submit to NIME 2015 at the 
<a href="http://precisionconference.com/%7Enime">NIME 2015 Submission Portal</a>.</p>

<p>Introduction
NIME (New Interfaces for Musical Expression) is the premier conference in designing human-computer interfaces and interactions for musical performance. NIME gathers researchers and practitioners around lectures, installations, concerts, and workshops.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Visual</td>
      <td>Aural</td>
      <td>Tangible</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Experimental Music &amp; Digital Media @ LSU
Louisiana State University and the city of Baton Rouge are excited to present the 15th edition of NIME. The LSU School of Music and Center for Computation &amp; Technology will host the 2015 NIME conference, sharing all that we have to offer to the NIME community to creatively explore how music is made. The conference will bridge a bit of past and future, with opportunities to engage in the fantastic musical history of Louisiana, as well as make use of the newly opened facilities at the LSU Digital Media Center including our 92-speaker immersive sound theatre. We are also excited to have the LSU Digital Art program involved in an expansion of the sonic art installations category for extended exhibition at the Shaw Center for the Arts, LSU Museum of Art and Glassell Gallery.</p>

<p>Laissez les bons temps rouler!</p>

<p>Call For Participation
On behalf of the NIME 2015 Committee, we would like to invite you to be part of the 15th international conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression.</p>

<p>We invite submission of new works in the following categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Papers and Posters</li>
  <li>Performances and Installations</li>
  <li>Workshops and Tutorials</li>
  <li>Demonstrations</li>
</ul>

<p>Important Dates</p>

<p>Artistic program: Performances &amp; Installation works</p>

<ul>
  <li>Submissions due: December 7, 2014</li>
  <li>Review Notification: January 30, 2015</li>
</ul>

<p>Scientific program: Papers, Workshops, Demonstrations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Draft submission (mandatory): January 23, 2015</li>
  <li>Final submission: January 30, 2015</li>
  <li>Review notification: March 20, 2015</li>
  <li>Camera-ready paper deadline: April 17, 2015</li>
</ul>

<p>The online submission system will open on November 3rd, 2014 and its address will be published at nime2015.lsu.edu</p>

<p>Please note the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The artistic program deadlines (installation and performance) this year do not coincide with the paper deadline!</li>
  <li>The scientific program consists of a mandatory draft submission followed by full submission. This system is implemented to address the perennial deadline extensions. There will be no deadline extensions. On the date of the draft submission, the author must be registered on the online submission system and have submitted a full draft manuscript of their paper. Authors then have one week to make minor edits to previously submitted manuscripts.</li>
</ul>

<p>Scientific Program</p>

<p>Call for Papers</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>We welcome submissions of original research on scientific and artistic use of new interfaces for musical expression. A non-exhaustive list of NIME related topics is found below. This list is inclusive and indicative. The thematic focus of this year’s edition is Visual</td>
      <td>Aural</td>
      <td>Tangible and is described in the introduction above. We also encourage submissions that extend, stretch, or challenge the NIME topics and themes.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Acceptance criteria: The paper under consideration must propose an original contribution to NIME research;; it must cite prior related work and should demonstrate rigorous research methodology.</p>

<p>There are three different paper submission categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Full paper (up to 6 pages in proceedings, longer oral presentation, optional demo)</li>
  <li>Short paper/poster (up to 4 pages in proceedings, shorter oral presentation or poster, optional demo)</li>
  <li>Demo paper (up to 2 pages in proceedings, demonstration)</li>
</ul>

<p>Submitted papers will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. All accepted papers will be published in the conference proceedings, under an ISSN/ISBN reference, and will be archived online after the conference to be tracked by citation tools. A manuscript submitted for review cannot be already under review for publication elsewhere or be submitted for a second review elsewhere while under review for NIME 2015. Authors of both full and short papers are greatly encouraged to submit a video in support of their paper. A video is mandatory for demonstration submission.</p>

<p>A best paper award will be presented to the individual(s) judged by the scientific committee to have written the best paper appearing in the conference proceedings.</p>

<p>In the aim to constantly improve the conference, this year the papers and demos will go through a modified review, which was first employed by NIME last year. The complete process is detailed below.</p>

<p>Call for Workshops</p>

<p>We invite submissions for half-day (3 hours) or full-day (6 hours) workshops and tutorials. These can be targeted towards specialist techniques, platforms, hardware, software or pedagogical topics for the advancement of fellow NIME-ers and people with experience related to the topic. They can also be targeted toward visitors to the NIME community, novices/newbies, interested student participants, people from other fields, and members of the public getting to know the potential of NIME.</p>

<p>Tutorial proposals should clearly indicate the audience and assumed knowledge of their intended participants to help us market to the appropriate audience. Workshops and tutorials can relate to, but are not limited to, the topics of the conference. This is a good opportunity to explore a specialized interest or interdisciplinary topic in depth with greater time for discourse, debate, and collaboration.</p>

<p>Review Process</p>

<p>After you submit your paper, it will go through a rigorous review process that has been changed compared to the previous years. Overall, the review process comprises three layers of evaluation: reviewer, meta-reviewer, and paper chair.</p>

<p>The process is as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Each paper is assigned to one meta-reviewer who is a representative of the general research topic that the paper deals with.</li>
  <li>The meta-reviewer together with the paper chair assign the papers to the reviewers that will evaluate it according to a set of criteria. Each paper has at least two reviewers.</li>
  <li>The meta-reviewer writes a meta-review based on the reviewers’ comments. The meta-reviewer may ask the reviewers to provide further details for reviews that were too concise.</li>
  <li>The paper chair gathers reviews and meta-reviews. He or she discusses with the meta-reviewers and finalizes a decision for each paper.</li>
  <li>The anonymity of the submission is preserved among the reviewers.</li>
</ul>

<p>Artistic Program</p>

<p>Call for Performances
We invite submission of proposals for performances and installations. Proposed performances should have a clear connection with the substance of the NIME conference. We expand the notion of NIME in the performance program to include the exploration of existing interfaces into new sounds, new methods, or new ways of being physical. These performances might re-insert the body into digital performance, or they might suggest new modes of performing and the presentation of live music that go beyond existing practices while exploiting the unique affordances of interfaces and technologies.</p>

<p>We encourage submissions that explore:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Novel and exploratory use of interfaces in performance</li>
  <li>Both old and new interfaces</li>
  <li>Use of innovative, imaginative and creative methods.</li>
</ul>

<p>We invite you to consider fully what a performance can be: you should go well beyond demonstrating the interface and we will consider any performance that is in the realm of live, electronically-produced sound, where an interface is central to the realisation of the music.</p>

<p>Submitted proposals will be reviewed by an expert committee. Preference will be given to submissions with strong evidence that the proposed performance has already been realized or is technically feasible and within the artists’ capabilities. We particularly invite premieres from performers with a track record, or with interfaces that have been well tested.</p>

<p>You should submit a PDF document, maximum 4 pages. The proposal must include the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Title and detailed description of the proposed performance.</li>
  <li>A link to one primary video documentation of an example performance with the relevant interface. If video documentation is inappropriate for your performance, please explain why and instead send an audio file with accompanying photographs (these do not need to be to marketing standard, they are more for explanation of how your performance will look).</li>
  <li>Links to any relevant supplementary supporting media files (audio and video).</li>
  <li>Number of performers and the instruments and technologies that will be used.</li>
  <li>Names of all participants/submitters, with a short bio for each (100 words).</li>
  <li>Details of technical requirements for the venue. Diagrams of the preferred stage setup and signal routing are recommended.</li>
  <li>Evidence of the feasibility of the performance. Include documentation and listings of past performances or related works that demonstrate the submitter’s capabilities to implement the proposed performance.</li>
  <li>A list of any equipment that needs to be provided by the conference organizers.</li>
  <li>Any instrumental performers that would need to be provided by the organizers. Note that the conference organizers may not be able to accommodate your request. Please also note that the organizers cannot provide funding to support performers’ travel or accommodation at the conference.</li>
  <li>Please specify if the performance is a demo.</li>
  <li>Please note whether performance would be better in club, bar or traditional concert environment.
Performance proposals in conjunction with paper submissions are encouraged, but each must be submitted separately and will be judged on its own merit.</li>
</ul>

<p>Typical NIME performance pieces last for 5-15 minutes, but shorter and longer performance proposals may exceptionally be taken into consideration.</p>

<p>Within reasonable limits, we may be able to provide musicians to perform pieces but this would be negotiated on a piece-by-piece basis.</p>

<p>Documentation of the performances will be available online after the conference unless this is impossible due to the nature of the performance.</p>

<p>Special Call – Digital Media Center Theatre</p>

<p>The LSU Center for Computation &amp; Technology’s Digital Media Center Theatre is a custom-designed immersive audio and video environment. The theatre hosts a Christie 4k digital projector, and a Meyer Constellation sound system, with 71 discrete channels and up to 40 directlyaccessibleaudiochannels. Weareinterestedinperformancesthatuse4kvideoand/or massively large loudspeaker arrays as essential components of the work. Also, demonstrations or papers that address massively large loudspeaker arrays are welcome. Contact us for more detailed specifications (nime-music@cct.lsu.edu).</p>

<p>Call for Installations</p>

<p>NIME 2015 seeks installation and sculptural work to showcase at several locations in Baton Rouge. The theme for all venues will focus on an amalgamation of NIME topics listed below. Special consideration will be given to projects that embody a combination of qualities that are visual, aural, and tangible. Submitted proposals will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. Installations picked to be shown at the LSU Digital Media Center will be exhibited during the length of the conference. Installations picked to be shown at the LSU Museum of Art and the LSU Glassell Gallery will be invited to be part of a longer exhibition spanning a month. These pieces will be shown alongside several invited sound artists whose work addresses NIME.</p>

<p>In order to present an installation for NIME 2015, please submit a proposal in the form of a PDF document, maximum 4 pages, containing the following information:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The title of the work</li>
  <li>Names of contributing artists</li>
  <li>A clear description of the proposed installation that will provide reviewers with a sense of its motivation and proposed realization. Pictures, schematic diagrams and/or proposed floor plans would be helpful here. You may also provide any documentation of previous presentations of this installation (if they exist).</li>
  <li>Describe the space needed and the adaptability of the installation in terms of possible venues.</li>
  <li>Provide a list of equipment required for the installation, clearly indicating what you will bring and what you would require the conference organizers to provide.</li>
  <li>Finally, indicate if your piece is able to be shown only during the length of the conference or if is able to remain for an extended exhibition.</li>
</ul>

<p>Topics</p>

<p>Core topics central to NIME include the following. In addition to submissions that address specific themes of this year’s edition of the conference, original contributions are encouraged in, but not limited to, the following topics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Novel controllers and interfaces for musical expression</li>
  <li>Novel musical instruments</li>
  <li>Augmented/hyper instruments</li>
  <li>Novel controllers for collaborative performance</li>
  <li>Sensor and actuator technologies</li>
  <li>Haptic and force feedback devices</li>
  <li>Motion, gesture and music</li>
  <li>Interfaces for dance and physical expression</li>
  <li>Multimodal expressive interfaces</li>
  <li>Interfaces for musical expression for hearing or visually impaired people</li>
  <li>Interactive game music</li>
  <li>NIME intersections with game design</li>
  <li>Robotic music</li>
  <li>Mobile music technology and performance paradigms</li>
  <li>Biological and bio-inspired systems</li>
  <li>Musical mapping strategies</li>
  <li>Embedded musical instruments and embedded sound art installations</li>
  <li>Interactive sound art and installations</li>
  <li>Musical human-computer interaction</li>
  <li>Interaction design and software tools</li>
  <li>Interface protocols and data formats</li>
  <li>Sonic interaction design</li>
  <li>Issues in perception, cognition, computational musicology and music analysis</li>
  <li>Performance analysis</li>
  <li>Performance rendering and generative algorithms</li>
  <li>Machine learning in musical performance</li>
  <li>Experiences with novel interfaces in live performance and composition</li>
  <li>Surveys of past work and stimulating ideas for future research</li>
  <li>Historical studies in twentieth-century instrument design</li>
  <li>Artistic, cultural, and social impact of NIME technology</li>
  <li>Novel interfaces in music education and entertainment</li>
  <li>Reports on student projects in the framework of NIME-related courses</li>
  <li>Practice-based research approaches/methodologies/criticism</li>
  <li>User studies/evaluations of NIME</li>
  <li>Language and state in live interaction</li>
  <li>Musicianship of new musical interfaces</li>
  <li>Platforms and frameworks for musical interaction design</li>
  <li>Organizing Committee</li>
</ul>

<p>NIME 2015 is hosted by the Cultural Computing focus area, Center for Computation &amp; Technology (
<a href="https://nime2015.lsu.edu/call-for-works/avatar.cct.lsu.edu">avatar.cct.lsu.edu</a>), and the LSU School of Music Experimental Music &amp; Digital Media program (
<a href="https://nime2015.lsu.edu/call-for-works/emdm.music.lsu.edu">emdm.music.lsu.edu</a>) at Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA.</p>

<p>General Inquiries: <a href="mailto:nime@cct.lsu.edu">nime@cct.lsu.edu</a>
Academic Inquiries: <a href="mailto:nime-papers@cct.lsu.edu">nime-papers@cct.lsu.edu</a>
Music Inquiries: <a href="mailto:nime-music@cct.lsu.edu">nime-music@cct.lsu.edu</a>
Installation: <a href="mailto:nime-art@cct.lsu.edu">nime-art@cct.lsu.edu</a>
Workshops: <a href="mailto:nime-workshops@cct.lsu.edu">nime-workshops@cct.lsu.edu</a>
Volunteers: <a href="mailto:nime-volunteer@cct.lsu.edu">nime-volunteer@cct.lsu.edu</a></p>

<p>© 2014 <a href="https://nime2015.lsu.edu"><strong>NIME 2015</strong></a> All Rights Reserved.</p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[May 31 – June 3, 2015 Louisiana State University Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA http://nime2015.lsu.edu Download the Call for Works here. Submit to NIME 2015 at the NIME 2015 Submission Portal. Introduction NIME (New Interfaces for Musical Expression) is the premier conference in designing human-computer interfaces and interactions for musical performance. NIME gathers researchers and practitioners around lectures, installations, concerts, and workshops. Visual Aural Tangible Experimental Music &amp; Digital Media @ LSU Louisiana State University and the city of Baton Rouge are excited to present the 15th edition of NIME. The LSU School of Music and Center for Computation &amp; Technology will host the 2015 NIME conference, sharing all that we have to offer to the NIME community to creatively explore how music is made. The conference will bridge a bit of past and future, with opportunities to engage in the fantastic musical history of Louisiana, as well as make use of the newly opened facilities at the LSU Digital Media Center including our 92-speaker immersive sound theatre. We are also excited to have the LSU Digital Art program involved in an expansion of the sonic art installations category for extended exhibition at the Shaw Center for the Arts, LSU Museum of Art and Glassell Gallery. Laissez les bons temps rouler! Call For Participation On behalf of the NIME 2015 Committee, we would like to invite you to be part of the 15th international conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression. We invite submission of new works in the following categories: Papers and Posters Performances and Installations Workshops and Tutorials Demonstrations Important Dates Artistic program: Performances &amp; Installation works Submissions due: December 7, 2014 Review Notification: January 30, 2015 Scientific program: Papers, Workshops, Demonstrations: Draft submission (mandatory): January 23, 2015 Final submission: January 30, 2015 Review notification: March 20, 2015 Camera-ready paper deadline: April 17, 2015 The online submission system will open on November 3rd, 2014 and its address will be published at nime2015.lsu.edu Please note the following: The artistic program deadlines (installation and performance) this year do not coincide with the paper deadline! The scientific program consists of a mandatory draft submission followed by full submission. This system is implemented to address the perennial deadline extensions. There will be no deadline extensions. On the date of the draft submission, the author must be registered on the online submission system and have submitted a full draft manuscript of their paper. Authors then have one week to make minor edits to previously submitted manuscripts. Scientific Program Call for Papers We welcome submissions of original research on scientific and artistic use of new interfaces for musical expression. A non-exhaustive list of NIME related topics is found below. This list is inclusive and indicative. The thematic focus of this year’s edition is Visual Aural Tangible and is described in the introduction above. We also encourage submissions that extend, stretch, or challenge the NIME topics and themes. Acceptance criteria: The paper under consideration must propose an original contribution to NIME research;; it must cite prior related work and should demonstrate rigorous research methodology. There are three different paper submission categories: Full paper (up to 6 pages in proceedings, longer oral presentation, optional demo) Short paper/poster (up to 4 pages in proceedings, shorter oral presentation or poster, optional demo) Demo paper (up to 2 pages in proceedings, demonstration) Submitted papers will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. All accepted papers will be published in the conference proceedings, under an ISSN/ISBN reference, and will be archived online after the conference to be tracked by citation tools. A manuscript submitted for review cannot be already under review for publication elsewhere or be submitted for a second review elsewhere while under review for NIME 2015. Authors of both full and short papers are greatly encouraged to submit a video in support of their paper. A video is mandatory for demonstration submission. A best paper award will be presented to the individual(s) judged by the scientific committee to have written the best paper appearing in the conference proceedings. In the aim to constantly improve the conference, this year the papers and demos will go through a modified review, which was first employed by NIME last year. The complete process is detailed below. Call for Workshops We invite submissions for half-day (3 hours) or full-day (6 hours) workshops and tutorials. These can be targeted towards specialist techniques, platforms, hardware, software or pedagogical topics for the advancement of fellow NIME-ers and people with experience related to the topic. They can also be targeted toward visitors to the NIME community, novices/newbies, interested student participants, people from other fields, and members of the public getting to know the potential of NIME. Tutorial proposals should clearly indicate the audience and assumed knowledge of their intended participants to help us market to the appropriate audience. Workshops and tutorials can relate to, but are not limited to, the topics of the conference. This is a good opportunity to explore a specialized interest or interdisciplinary topic in depth with greater time for discourse, debate, and collaboration. Review Process After you submit your paper, it will go through a rigorous review process that has been changed compared to the previous years. Overall, the review process comprises three layers of evaluation: reviewer, meta-reviewer, and paper chair. The process is as follows: Each paper is assigned to one meta-reviewer who is a representative of the general research topic that the paper deals with. The meta-reviewer together with the paper chair assign the papers to the reviewers that will evaluate it according to a set of criteria. Each paper has at least two reviewers. The meta-reviewer writes a meta-review based on the reviewers’ comments. The meta-reviewer may ask the reviewers to provide further details for reviews that were too concise. The paper chair gathers reviews and meta-reviews. He or she discusses with the meta-reviewers and finalizes a decision for each paper. The anonymity of the submission is preserved among the reviewers. Artistic Program Call for Performances We invite submission of proposals for performances and installations. Proposed performances should have a clear connection with the substance of the NIME conference. We expand the notion of NIME in the performance program to include the exploration of existing interfaces into new sounds, new methods, or new ways of being physical. These performances might re-insert the body into digital performance, or they might suggest new modes of performing and the presentation of live music that go beyond existing practices while exploiting the unique affordances of interfaces and technologies. We encourage submissions that explore: Novel and exploratory use of interfaces in performance Both old and new interfaces Use of innovative, imaginative and creative methods. We invite you to consider fully what a performance can be: you should go well beyond demonstrating the interface and we will consider any performance that is in the realm of live, electronically-produced sound, where an interface is central to the realisation of the music. Submitted proposals will be reviewed by an expert committee. Preference will be given to submissions with strong evidence that the proposed performance has already been realized or is technically feasible and within the artists’ capabilities. We particularly invite premieres from performers with a track record, or with interfaces that have been well tested. You should submit a PDF document, maximum 4 pages. The proposal must include the following: Title and detailed description of the proposed performance. A link to one primary video documentation of an example performance with the relevant interface. If video documentation is inappropriate for your performance, please explain why and instead send an audio file with accompanying photographs (these do not need to be to marketing standard, they are more for explanation of how your performance will look). Links to any relevant supplementary supporting media files (audio and video). Number of performers and the instruments and technologies that will be used. Names of all participants/submitters, with a short bio for each (100 words). Details of technical requirements for the venue. Diagrams of the preferred stage setup and signal routing are recommended. Evidence of the feasibility of the performance. Include documentation and listings of past performances or related works that demonstrate the submitter’s capabilities to implement the proposed performance. A list of any equipment that needs to be provided by the conference organizers. Any instrumental performers that would need to be provided by the organizers. Note that the conference organizers may not be able to accommodate your request. Please also note that the organizers cannot provide funding to support performers’ travel or accommodation at the conference. Please specify if the performance is a demo. Please note whether performance would be better in club, bar or traditional concert environment. Performance proposals in conjunction with paper submissions are encouraged, but each must be submitted separately and will be judged on its own merit. Typical NIME performance pieces last for 5-15 minutes, but shorter and longer performance proposals may exceptionally be taken into consideration. Within reasonable limits, we may be able to provide musicians to perform pieces but this would be negotiated on a piece-by-piece basis. Documentation of the performances will be available online after the conference unless this is impossible due to the nature of the performance. Special Call – Digital Media Center Theatre The LSU Center for Computation &amp; Technology’s Digital Media Center Theatre is a custom-designed immersive audio and video environment. The theatre hosts a Christie 4k digital projector, and a Meyer Constellation sound system, with 71 discrete channels and up to 40 directlyaccessibleaudiochannels. Weareinterestedinperformancesthatuse4kvideoand/or massively large loudspeaker arrays as essential components of the work. Also, demonstrations or papers that address massively large loudspeaker arrays are welcome. Contact us for more detailed specifications (nime-music@cct.lsu.edu). Call for Installations NIME 2015 seeks installation and sculptural work to showcase at several locations in Baton Rouge. The theme for all venues will focus on an amalgamation of NIME topics listed below. Special consideration will be given to projects that embody a combination of qualities that are visual, aural, and tangible. Submitted proposals will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. Installations picked to be shown at the LSU Digital Media Center will be exhibited during the length of the conference. Installations picked to be shown at the LSU Museum of Art and the LSU Glassell Gallery will be invited to be part of a longer exhibition spanning a month. These pieces will be shown alongside several invited sound artists whose work addresses NIME. In order to present an installation for NIME 2015, please submit a proposal in the form of a PDF document, maximum 4 pages, containing the following information: The title of the work Names of contributing artists A clear description of the proposed installation that will provide reviewers with a sense of its motivation and proposed realization. Pictures, schematic diagrams and/or proposed floor plans would be helpful here. You may also provide any documentation of previous presentations of this installation (if they exist). Describe the space needed and the adaptability of the installation in terms of possible venues. Provide a list of equipment required for the installation, clearly indicating what you will bring and what you would require the conference organizers to provide. Finally, indicate if your piece is able to be shown only during the length of the conference or if is able to remain for an extended exhibition. Topics Core topics central to NIME include the following. In addition to submissions that address specific themes of this year’s edition of the conference, original contributions are encouraged in, but not limited to, the following topics: Novel controllers and interfaces for musical expression Novel musical instruments Augmented/hyper instruments Novel controllers for collaborative performance Sensor and actuator technologies Haptic and force feedback devices Motion, gesture and music Interfaces for dance and physical expression Multimodal expressive interfaces Interfaces for musical expression for hearing or visually impaired people Interactive game music NIME intersections with game design Robotic music Mobile music technology and performance paradigms Biological and bio-inspired systems Musical mapping strategies Embedded musical instruments and embedded sound art installations Interactive sound art and installations Musical human-computer interaction Interaction design and software tools Interface protocols and data formats Sonic interaction design Issues in perception, cognition, computational musicology and music analysis Performance analysis Performance rendering and generative algorithms Machine learning in musical performance Experiences with novel interfaces in live performance and composition Surveys of past work and stimulating ideas for future research Historical studies in twentieth-century instrument design Artistic, cultural, and social impact of NIME technology Novel interfaces in music education and entertainment Reports on student projects in the framework of NIME-related courses Practice-based research approaches/methodologies/criticism User studies/evaluations of NIME Language and state in live interaction Musicianship of new musical interfaces Platforms and frameworks for musical interaction design Organizing Committee NIME 2015 is hosted by the Cultural Computing focus area, Center for Computation &amp; Technology ( avatar.cct.lsu.edu), and the LSU School of Music Experimental Music &amp; Digital Media program ( emdm.music.lsu.edu) at Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA. General Inquiries: nime@cct.lsu.edu Academic Inquiries: nime-papers@cct.lsu.edu Music Inquiries: nime-music@cct.lsu.edu Installation: nime-art@cct.lsu.edu Workshops: nime-workshops@cct.lsu.edu Volunteers: nime-volunteer@cct.lsu.edu © 2014 NIME 2015 All Rights Reserved.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NIME 2014 - Call for Participation</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2013/09/20/nime2014/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NIME 2014 - Call for Participation" /><published>2013-09-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-09-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2013/09/20/nime2014</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2013/09/20/nime2014/"><![CDATA[<p>Please visit <a href="http://www.nime.org/2014/">http://www.nime.org/2014/</a> for more information such as submission website, contacts, etc.<em>**</em></p>

<p><img src="/nime/assets/logos/nime2014.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>14th International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression (NIME)</p>

<p>June 30 - July 3, 2014
Goldsmiths, University of London
London, UK</p>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>NIME (New Interfaces for Musical Expression) is the premier conference in designing human-computer interfaces and interactions for musical performance. NIME gathers researchers and practitioners around lectures, installations, concerts, and workshops. We are delighted to host NIME 2014 at Goldsmiths, University of London, bringing NIME for the first time to London and situating the conference within highly developed UK research networks in music computing, media, design, and HCI, and connecting NIME research to a thriving local music scene, art, and interaction design communities.</p>

<p>In its second decade, one can say that NIME, as a field, has “arrived.” Sensing technology is ubiquitous in consumer products like smart-phones and video game controllers. Computer-based music performance is no longer contained in specialised genres, but has become the norm in a broad range of musical styles. The success of interactive music technologies puts in question the very need for NIME to even exist.</p>

<p>The take-up of NIME techniques in all music causes the technology to disappear and forces us to focus on the music. This represents a double-edged sword. While the focus on musical quality is paramount, it can only be built upon foundations of solid craft and excellent science. In order to avoid re-inventing the wheel, and worse yet, repeating mistakes, NIME needs to build a legacy of reproducible results, citable references, and transferrable methods and techniques that can be transmitted to students, broader groups of musicians, and amateurs eager to engage in richer musical experiences.</p>

<p>New instruments and interaction are at the heart of NIME. Lutherie and composition combine to create the means to deliver compelling live performances. This is an ideal, and is more often than not, assumed. In between the science of interaction and the art of music-making are the cultural and theoretical considerations about what comprises an exciting performance.</p>

<p>With the theme Liveness, we draw upon Philip Auslander’s reading of this seemingly simple word as a way to look at issues of authenticity, experience, and the role that theatricality and mediatization might play in reinforcing or detracting from a successful performer/audience dynamic.</p>

<p>We will build upon a productive history of collaboration between Goldsmiths and Brunel University in the Brunel Electronic and Analogue Music (BEAM) festival to bring added excitement to the NIME 2014 concert and exhibition programme. We will partner with high profile venues such as Café Oto and DIY communities like London Music Hackspace to open up the NIME artistic programme to the general public and connect our research community to the thriving music scene in London.</p>

<h2 id="call-for-participation">Call for Participation</h2>

<p>On behalf of the NIME 2014 Committee, we would like to invite you to be part of the 14th international conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression.</p>

<p>We invite submission of new works in the following categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Papers and Posters</li>
  <li>Performances and Installations</li>
  <li>Workshops and Tutorials</li>
  <li>Demonstrations and Demo-performances</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="important-dates">IMPORTANT DATES:</h3>

<p>Artistic programme: Performances &amp; Installation works</p>

<p>Submissions due: <strong>December 1, 2013</strong></p>

<p>Review Notification: <strong>February 1, 2014</strong></p>

<p>Scientific programme: Papers, Workshops, Demonstrations:
Draft submission (mandatory): <strong>January 31, 2014</strong></p>

<p>Final submission: <strong>February 7, 2014</strong></p>

<p>Review notification: <strong>March 28, 2014</strong></p>

<p>Camera-ready paper deadline: <strong>April 18, 2014</strong></p>

<p>An online submission system will open on November 15th, 2013 and its address will be published here.</p>

<p>N.B. Please note that the art programme deadline this year does not coincide with the paper deadline.</p>

<p>N.B. Note the new system in the scientific programme for mandatory draft submission followed by full submission. We have implemented this new system to address the perennial deadline extensions. This year, we will not offer extensions. The Draft Submission deadline corresponds to previous years’ submission deadline. On this date, the author must be registered on the online submission system and have submitted a full draft manuscript of their paper. You will then have one week (the time of prior years’ extensions) to make minor edits to your manuscript.</p>

<h2 id="scientific-programme">Scientific Programme</h2>

<h3 id="call-for-papers">CALL FOR PAPERS</h3>

<p>We welcome submissions of original research on scientific and artistic use of new interfaces for musical expression. A non-exhaustive list of NIME related topics is found below. This list is inclusive, and indicative. The thematic focus of this year’s edition is Liveness, and is described in the introduction above. We also encourage submissions that extend, stretch, or challenge the NIME topics and themes.</p>

<p>Acceptance criteria: The paper under consideration must propose an original contribution to NIME research; it must cite prior related work and should demonstrate rigorous research methodology.</p>

<p>There are three different paper submission categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Full paper (up to 6 pages in proceedings, longer oral presentation, optional demo)</li>
  <li>Short paper/poster (up to 4 pages in proceedings, shorter oral presentation or poster, optional demo)</li>
  <li>Demo paper (up to 2 pages in proceedings, demonstration)</li>
</ul>

<p>Submitted papers will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. All accepted papers will be published in the conference proceedings, under an ISSN/ISBN reference, and will be archived online after the conference to be tracked by citation tools. A manuscript submitted for review cannot be already under review for publication elsewhere, or be submitted for a second review elsewhere while under review for NIME 2014. Authors of both full and short papers are greatly encouraged to submit a video in support of their paper. A video is mandatory for demonstration submission.</p>

<p>A best paper award will be presented to the individual(s) judged by the scientific committee to have written the best paper appearing in the conference proceedings.</p>

<p>In the aim to constantly improve the conference, this year the papers and demos will go through a modified review process compared to the previous years. The complete process is detailed <a href="#reviewprocesspapers">below</a>.</p>

<h3 id="call-for-workshops">CALL FOR WORKSHOPS</h3>

<p>We invite submissions for half-day (3 hours) or full-day (6 hours) workshops and tutorials. These can be targeted towards specialist techniques, platforms, hardware, software or pedagogical topics for the advancement of fellow NIME-ers and people with experience related to the topic. They can also be targeted towards visitors to the NIME community, novices/newbies, interested student participants, people from other fields, and members of the public getting to know the potential of NIME.</p>

<p>Tutorial proposals should clearly indicate the audience and assumed knowledge of their intended participants to help us market to the appropriate audience. Workshops and tutorials can relate to, but are not limited to, the topics of the conference. This is a good opportunity to explore a specialized interest or interdisciplinary topic in depth with greater time for discourse, debate, and collaboration.</p>

<h3 id="review-process">REVIEW PROCESS</h3>

<p>After you submit your paper, it will go through a rigorous review process that has been changed compared to the previous years. Overall, the review process comprises three layers of evaluation: reviewer, meta-reviewer and scientific chairs. The process is as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Each paper is assigned to one meta-reviewer who is a representative of the general research topic that the paper deals with.</li>
  <li>The meta-reviewer together with the scientific chairs are assigning the papers to the reviewers that will evaluate it according to a set of criteria. Each paper has at least two reviewers.</li>
  <li>The meta-reviewer writes a meta-review based on the reviewers’ comments. The meta-reviewer may ask further details to a reviewer in case the produced comments are too concise.</li>
  <li>The scientific chairs gather reviews and meta-reviews. They discuss with the meta-reviewers and finalize a decision for each paper.</li>
  <li>The anonymity of the submission is preserved all along the review process.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="artistic-programme">Artistic Programme</h2>

<h3 id="call-for-performances--installations">CALL FOR PERFORMANCES &amp; INSTALLATIONS</h3>

<p>We invite submission of proposals for performances and installations. Proposed performances should have a clear connection with the substance of the NIME conference. We expand the notion of NIME in the performance programme, to include the exploration of existing interfaces into new sounds, new methods or new ways of being physical. These performances might re-insert the body into digital performance, or they might suggest new modes of performing and the presentation of live music that go beyond existing practices whilst exploiting the unique affordances of interfaces and technologies.</p>

<p>We encourage submissions that explore:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Novel and exploratory use of interfaces in performance</li>
  <li>Both old and new interfaces</li>
  <li>Use of innovative, imaginative and creative methods.</li>
</ul>

<p>We invite you to consider fully what a performance can be: you should go well beyond demonstrating the interface and we will consider any performance that is in the realm of live, electronically-produced sound, where an interface is central to the realisation of the music.</p>

<p>Submitted proposals will be reviewed by an expert committee. Preference will be given to submissions with strong evidence that the proposed performance has already been realized or is technically feasible and within the artists’ capabilities. We particularly invite premieres from performers with a track record, or with interfaces that have been well tested.</p>

<h3 id="call-for-demo-performances">CALL FOR DEMO-PERFORMANCES</h3>

<p>This year, we introduce a hybrid zone between the artistic and scientific programme by creating a new category of demonstration-performance. This is particularly apt for new interfaces and performance sketches which are still in the testing or early artistic phase. A lively demo session will allow you to set up your piece or instrument and give short performances in an unstaged setting.</p>

<h3 id="performance-submission-format">PERFORMANCE SUBMISSION FORMAT</h3>

<p>You should submit a PDF document, maximum 4 pages. The proposal must include the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Title and detailed description of the proposed performance.</li>
  <li>A link to one primary video documentation of an example performance with the relevant interface. If video documentation is inappropriate for your performance, please explain why and instead send an audio file with accompanying photographs (these do not need to be to marketing standard, they are more for explanation of how your performance will look).</li>
  <li>Links to any relevant supplementary supporting media files (audio and video).</li>
  <li>Number of performers and the instruments and technologies that will be used.</li>
  <li>Names of all participants/submitters, with a short bio for each (100 words).</li>
  <li>Details of technical requirements for the venue. Diagrams of the preferred stage setup and signal routing are recommended.</li>
  <li>Evidence of the feasibility of the performance. Include documentation and listings of past performances or related works that demonstrate the submitter’s capabilities to implement the proposed performance.</li>
  <li>A list of any equipment that needs to be provided by the conference organizers.</li>
  <li>Any instrumental performers that would need to be provided by the organizers. Note that the conference organizers may not be able to accommodate your request. Please also note that the organizers cannot provide funding to support performers’ travel or accommodation at the conference.</li>
  <li>Please specify if the performance is a demo.</li>
  <li>Please note whether performance would be better in club, bar or traditional concert environment.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="installation-submission-format">INSTALLATION SUBMISSION FORMAT</h3>

<p>NIME 2014 will provide several locations for sound installations. Submitted proposals will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. In order to present an installation for NIME 2014, please submit a proposal in the form of a PDF document, maximum 4 pages, containing the following information:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The title of the work</li>
  <li>Names of contributing artists</li>
  <li>A clear description of the proposed installation that will provide reviewers with a sense of its motivation and proposed realization. Pictures, schematic diagrams and/or proposed floor plans would be helpful here. You may also provide any documentation of previous presentations of this installation (if they exist)</li>
  <li>Describe the space needed and the adaptability of the installation in terms of possible venues.</li>
  <li>Provide a list of equipment required for the installation, clearly indicating what you will bring and what you would require the conference organizers to provide.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="notes">NOTES</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Performance proposals in conjunction with paper submissions are allowed, but each will be judged on its own merit.</li>
  <li>Typical NIME performance pieces last for 5-15 minutes, but shorter and longer performance proposals may exceptionally be taken into consideration.</li>
  <li>Within reasonable limits, we may be able to provide musicians to perform pieces but this would be negotiated on a piece-by-piece basis.</li>
  <li>Documentation of the performances will be available online after the conference unless this is impossible due to the nature of the performance.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="topics">Topics</h2>

<p>Core topics central to NIME include the following. In addition to submissions that address specific themes of this year’s edition of the conference, original contributions are encouraged in, but not limited to, the following topics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Novel controllers and interfaces for musical expression</li>
  <li>Novel musical instruments</li>
  <li>Augmented/hyper instruments</li>
  <li>Novel controllers for collaborative performance</li>
  <li>Sensor and actuator technologies</li>
  <li>Haptic and force feedback devices</li>
  <li>Motion, gesture and music</li>
  <li>Interfaces for dance and physical expression</li>
  <li>Multimodal expressive interfaces</li>
  <li>Interfaces for musical expression for hearing or visually impaired people</li>
  <li>Interactive game music</li>
  <li>NIME intersecting with game design</li>
  <li>Robotic music</li>
  <li>Mobile music technology and performance paradigms</li>
  <li>Biological and bio-inspired systems</li>
  <li>Musical mapping strategies</li>
  <li>Interactive sound and multimedia installations</li>
  <li>Musical human-computer interaction</li>
  <li>Interaction design and software tools</li>
  <li>Interface protocols and data formats</li>
  <li>Sonic interaction design</li>
  <li>Perceptual and cognitive issues</li>
  <li>Performance analysis</li>
  <li>Performance rendering and generative algorithms</li>
  <li>Machine learning in musical performance</li>
  <li>Experiences with novel interfaces in live performance and composition</li>
  <li>Surveys of past work and stimulating ideas for future research</li>
  <li>Historical studies in twentieth-century instrument design</li>
  <li>Artistic, cultural, and social impact of NIME technology</li>
  <li>Novel interfaces in music education and entertainment</li>
  <li>Reports on student projects in the framework of NIME related courses</li>
  <li>Practice-based research approaches/methodologies/criticism</li>
  <li>User studies/evaluations of NIME</li>
  <li>Language and state in live interaction</li>
  <li>Musicianship of new musical interfaces</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="organizing-committee">Organizing Committee</h2>

<p>NIME 2014 is hosted by the EAVI group 
<a href="http://eavi.goldsmithsdigital.com">eavi.goldsmithsdigital.com</a> at Goldsmiths, University of London, UK.</p>

<p>General Co-chairs</p>

<p><strong>Atau Tanaka</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p><strong>Rebecca Fiebrink</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p>Scientific Co-chairs</p>

<p><strong>Baptiste Caramiaux</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p><strong>Koray Tahiroğlu</strong>
 (Aalto University, Helsinki)</p>

<p>Artistic Co-chairs</p>

<p><strong>Sarah Nicolls</strong>
 (Brunel University)</p>

<p><strong>Adam Parkinson</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p>Posters and Demos Co-chairs</p>

<p><strong>Marco Donnarumma</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p><strong>Alessandro Altavilla</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p>Special Sessions Co-chairs</p>

<p><strong>Marco Gillies</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p><strong>Alex McLean</strong>
 (University of Leeds)</p>

<p><strong>Jean-Baptiste Thiebaut</strong>
 (ROLI/Music Hackspace)</p>

<p>Student Volunteer Coordinators</p>

<p><strong>Peter Mackenzie</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p><strong>Anna Weisling</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p>Conference Producer</p>

<p><strong>Stephanie Horak</strong>
 (Goldsmiths)</p>

<p> </p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please visit http://www.nime.org/2014/ for more information such as submission website, contacts, etc.** 14th International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression (NIME) June 30 - July 3, 2014 Goldsmiths, University of London London, UK Introduction NIME (New Interfaces for Musical Expression) is the premier conference in designing human-computer interfaces and interactions for musical performance. NIME gathers researchers and practitioners around lectures, installations, concerts, and workshops. We are delighted to host NIME 2014 at Goldsmiths, University of London, bringing NIME for the first time to London and situating the conference within highly developed UK research networks in music computing, media, design, and HCI, and connecting NIME research to a thriving local music scene, art, and interaction design communities. In its second decade, one can say that NIME, as a field, has “arrived.” Sensing technology is ubiquitous in consumer products like smart-phones and video game controllers. Computer-based music performance is no longer contained in specialised genres, but has become the norm in a broad range of musical styles. The success of interactive music technologies puts in question the very need for NIME to even exist. The take-up of NIME techniques in all music causes the technology to disappear and forces us to focus on the music. This represents a double-edged sword. While the focus on musical quality is paramount, it can only be built upon foundations of solid craft and excellent science. In order to avoid re-inventing the wheel, and worse yet, repeating mistakes, NIME needs to build a legacy of reproducible results, citable references, and transferrable methods and techniques that can be transmitted to students, broader groups of musicians, and amateurs eager to engage in richer musical experiences. New instruments and interaction are at the heart of NIME. Lutherie and composition combine to create the means to deliver compelling live performances. This is an ideal, and is more often than not, assumed. In between the science of interaction and the art of music-making are the cultural and theoretical considerations about what comprises an exciting performance. With the theme Liveness, we draw upon Philip Auslander’s reading of this seemingly simple word as a way to look at issues of authenticity, experience, and the role that theatricality and mediatization might play in reinforcing or detracting from a successful performer/audience dynamic. We will build upon a productive history of collaboration between Goldsmiths and Brunel University in the Brunel Electronic and Analogue Music (BEAM) festival to bring added excitement to the NIME 2014 concert and exhibition programme. We will partner with high profile venues such as Café Oto and DIY communities like London Music Hackspace to open up the NIME artistic programme to the general public and connect our research community to the thriving music scene in London. Call for Participation On behalf of the NIME 2014 Committee, we would like to invite you to be part of the 14th international conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression. We invite submission of new works in the following categories: Papers and Posters Performances and Installations Workshops and Tutorials Demonstrations and Demo-performances IMPORTANT DATES: Artistic programme: Performances &amp; Installation works Submissions due: December 1, 2013 Review Notification: February 1, 2014 Scientific programme: Papers, Workshops, Demonstrations: Draft submission (mandatory): January 31, 2014 Final submission: February 7, 2014 Review notification: March 28, 2014 Camera-ready paper deadline: April 18, 2014 An online submission system will open on November 15th, 2013 and its address will be published here. N.B. Please note that the art programme deadline this year does not coincide with the paper deadline. N.B. Note the new system in the scientific programme for mandatory draft submission followed by full submission. We have implemented this new system to address the perennial deadline extensions. This year, we will not offer extensions. The Draft Submission deadline corresponds to previous years’ submission deadline. On this date, the author must be registered on the online submission system and have submitted a full draft manuscript of their paper. You will then have one week (the time of prior years’ extensions) to make minor edits to your manuscript. Scientific Programme CALL FOR PAPERS We welcome submissions of original research on scientific and artistic use of new interfaces for musical expression. A non-exhaustive list of NIME related topics is found below. This list is inclusive, and indicative. The thematic focus of this year’s edition is Liveness, and is described in the introduction above. We also encourage submissions that extend, stretch, or challenge the NIME topics and themes. Acceptance criteria: The paper under consideration must propose an original contribution to NIME research; it must cite prior related work and should demonstrate rigorous research methodology. There are three different paper submission categories: Full paper (up to 6 pages in proceedings, longer oral presentation, optional demo) Short paper/poster (up to 4 pages in proceedings, shorter oral presentation or poster, optional demo) Demo paper (up to 2 pages in proceedings, demonstration) Submitted papers will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. All accepted papers will be published in the conference proceedings, under an ISSN/ISBN reference, and will be archived online after the conference to be tracked by citation tools. A manuscript submitted for review cannot be already under review for publication elsewhere, or be submitted for a second review elsewhere while under review for NIME 2014. Authors of both full and short papers are greatly encouraged to submit a video in support of their paper. A video is mandatory for demonstration submission. A best paper award will be presented to the individual(s) judged by the scientific committee to have written the best paper appearing in the conference proceedings. In the aim to constantly improve the conference, this year the papers and demos will go through a modified review process compared to the previous years. The complete process is detailed below. CALL FOR WORKSHOPS We invite submissions for half-day (3 hours) or full-day (6 hours) workshops and tutorials. These can be targeted towards specialist techniques, platforms, hardware, software or pedagogical topics for the advancement of fellow NIME-ers and people with experience related to the topic. They can also be targeted towards visitors to the NIME community, novices/newbies, interested student participants, people from other fields, and members of the public getting to know the potential of NIME. Tutorial proposals should clearly indicate the audience and assumed knowledge of their intended participants to help us market to the appropriate audience. Workshops and tutorials can relate to, but are not limited to, the topics of the conference. This is a good opportunity to explore a specialized interest or interdisciplinary topic in depth with greater time for discourse, debate, and collaboration. REVIEW PROCESS After you submit your paper, it will go through a rigorous review process that has been changed compared to the previous years. Overall, the review process comprises three layers of evaluation: reviewer, meta-reviewer and scientific chairs. The process is as follows: Each paper is assigned to one meta-reviewer who is a representative of the general research topic that the paper deals with. The meta-reviewer together with the scientific chairs are assigning the papers to the reviewers that will evaluate it according to a set of criteria. Each paper has at least two reviewers. The meta-reviewer writes a meta-review based on the reviewers’ comments. The meta-reviewer may ask further details to a reviewer in case the produced comments are too concise. The scientific chairs gather reviews and meta-reviews. They discuss with the meta-reviewers and finalize a decision for each paper. The anonymity of the submission is preserved all along the review process. Artistic Programme CALL FOR PERFORMANCES &amp; INSTALLATIONS We invite submission of proposals for performances and installations. Proposed performances should have a clear connection with the substance of the NIME conference. We expand the notion of NIME in the performance programme, to include the exploration of existing interfaces into new sounds, new methods or new ways of being physical. These performances might re-insert the body into digital performance, or they might suggest new modes of performing and the presentation of live music that go beyond existing practices whilst exploiting the unique affordances of interfaces and technologies. We encourage submissions that explore: Novel and exploratory use of interfaces in performance Both old and new interfaces Use of innovative, imaginative and creative methods. We invite you to consider fully what a performance can be: you should go well beyond demonstrating the interface and we will consider any performance that is in the realm of live, electronically-produced sound, where an interface is central to the realisation of the music. Submitted proposals will be reviewed by an expert committee. Preference will be given to submissions with strong evidence that the proposed performance has already been realized or is technically feasible and within the artists’ capabilities. We particularly invite premieres from performers with a track record, or with interfaces that have been well tested. CALL FOR DEMO-PERFORMANCES This year, we introduce a hybrid zone between the artistic and scientific programme by creating a new category of demonstration-performance. This is particularly apt for new interfaces and performance sketches which are still in the testing or early artistic phase. A lively demo session will allow you to set up your piece or instrument and give short performances in an unstaged setting. PERFORMANCE SUBMISSION FORMAT You should submit a PDF document, maximum 4 pages. The proposal must include the following: Title and detailed description of the proposed performance. A link to one primary video documentation of an example performance with the relevant interface. If video documentation is inappropriate for your performance, please explain why and instead send an audio file with accompanying photographs (these do not need to be to marketing standard, they are more for explanation of how your performance will look). Links to any relevant supplementary supporting media files (audio and video). Number of performers and the instruments and technologies that will be used. Names of all participants/submitters, with a short bio for each (100 words). Details of technical requirements for the venue. Diagrams of the preferred stage setup and signal routing are recommended. Evidence of the feasibility of the performance. Include documentation and listings of past performances or related works that demonstrate the submitter’s capabilities to implement the proposed performance. A list of any equipment that needs to be provided by the conference organizers. Any instrumental performers that would need to be provided by the organizers. Note that the conference organizers may not be able to accommodate your request. Please also note that the organizers cannot provide funding to support performers’ travel or accommodation at the conference. Please specify if the performance is a demo. Please note whether performance would be better in club, bar or traditional concert environment. INSTALLATION SUBMISSION FORMAT NIME 2014 will provide several locations for sound installations. Submitted proposals will be subject to a peer review process by an international expert committee. In order to present an installation for NIME 2014, please submit a proposal in the form of a PDF document, maximum 4 pages, containing the following information: The title of the work Names of contributing artists A clear description of the proposed installation that will provide reviewers with a sense of its motivation and proposed realization. Pictures, schematic diagrams and/or proposed floor plans would be helpful here. You may also provide any documentation of previous presentations of this installation (if they exist) Describe the space needed and the adaptability of the installation in terms of possible venues. Provide a list of equipment required for the installation, clearly indicating what you will bring and what you would require the conference organizers to provide. NOTES Performance proposals in conjunction with paper submissions are allowed, but each will be judged on its own merit. Typical NIME performance pieces last for 5-15 minutes, but shorter and longer performance proposals may exceptionally be taken into consideration. Within reasonable limits, we may be able to provide musicians to perform pieces but this would be negotiated on a piece-by-piece basis. Documentation of the performances will be available online after the conference unless this is impossible due to the nature of the performance. Topics Core topics central to NIME include the following. In addition to submissions that address specific themes of this year’s edition of the conference, original contributions are encouraged in, but not limited to, the following topics: Novel controllers and interfaces for musical expression Novel musical instruments Augmented/hyper instruments Novel controllers for collaborative performance Sensor and actuator technologies Haptic and force feedback devices Motion, gesture and music Interfaces for dance and physical expression Multimodal expressive interfaces Interfaces for musical expression for hearing or visually impaired people Interactive game music NIME intersecting with game design Robotic music Mobile music technology and performance paradigms Biological and bio-inspired systems Musical mapping strategies Interactive sound and multimedia installations Musical human-computer interaction Interaction design and software tools Interface protocols and data formats Sonic interaction design Perceptual and cognitive issues Performance analysis Performance rendering and generative algorithms Machine learning in musical performance Experiences with novel interfaces in live performance and composition Surveys of past work and stimulating ideas for future research Historical studies in twentieth-century instrument design Artistic, cultural, and social impact of NIME technology Novel interfaces in music education and entertainment Reports on student projects in the framework of NIME related courses Practice-based research approaches/methodologies/criticism User studies/evaluations of NIME Language and state in live interaction Musicianship of new musical interfaces Organizing Committee NIME 2014 is hosted by the EAVI group eavi.goldsmithsdigital.com at Goldsmiths, University of London, UK. General Co-chairs Atau Tanaka (Goldsmiths) Rebecca Fiebrink (Goldsmiths) Scientific Co-chairs Baptiste Caramiaux (Goldsmiths) Koray Tahiroğlu (Aalto University, Helsinki) Artistic Co-chairs Sarah Nicolls (Brunel University) Adam Parkinson (Goldsmiths) Posters and Demos Co-chairs Marco Donnarumma (Goldsmiths) Alessandro Altavilla (Goldsmiths) Special Sessions Co-chairs Marco Gillies (Goldsmiths) Alex McLean (University of Leeds) Jean-Baptiste Thiebaut (ROLI/Music Hackspace) Student Volunteer Coordinators Peter Mackenzie (Goldsmiths) Anna Weisling (Goldsmiths) Conference Producer Stephanie Horak (Goldsmiths)  ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NIME 2013 announced</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2012/05/29/nime-2013-announced/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NIME 2013 announced" /><published>2012-05-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-05-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2012/05/29/nime-2013-announced</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/uncategorized/2012/05/29/nime-2013-announced/"><![CDATA[<p>NIME 2013 will be held at KAIST (Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology), Daejeon, Korea, and will feature a series of special events in Seoul.</p>

<p>More information will be available at <a href="http://www.nime2013.org">nime2013.org</a> soon.</p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[NIME 2013 will be held at KAIST (Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology), Daejeon, Korea, and will feature a series of special events in Seoul. More information will be available at nime2013.org soon.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New NIME Website !</title><link href="https://nime.org/nime/website/2012/03/23/new-nime-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New NIME Website !" /><published>2012-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nime.org/nime/website/2012/03/23/new-nime-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nime.org/nime/website/2012/03/23/new-nime-website/"><![CDATA[<p>It is a real pleasure for us to unveil this new NIME website. It has been a great effort from the Steering Committee to provide a whole new web experience for materials related to the International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression. One significant improvement is the archiving and indexing of all the proceedings, that we hope will bring an easier way for all of you to find and cite NIME papers. The platform that we have now installed is expected to grow with more services: photos, videos, special pages, etc. If you have any questions or requests, feel free to comment on this post or send an email to the <a href="http://www.nime.org/committee/">Steering Committee</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>NIMEconference</name></author><category term="Website" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is a real pleasure for us to unveil this new NIME website. It has been a great effort from the Steering Committee to provide a whole new web experience for materials related to the International Conference on New Interfaces for Musical Expression. One significant improvement is the archiving and indexing of all the proceedings, that we hope will bring an easier way for all of you to find and cite NIME papers. The platform that we have now installed is expected to grow with more services: photos, videos, special pages, etc. If you have any questions or requests, feel free to comment on this post or send an email to the Steering Committee.]]></summary></entry></feed>